<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE Publisher PUBLIC "-//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN" "http://devel.springer.de/A++/V2.4/DTD/A++V2.4.dtd">
<Publisher>
  <PublisherInfo>
    <PublisherName>Springer International Publishing</PublisherName>
    <PublisherLocation>Cham</PublisherLocation>
    <PublisherImprintName>Springer</PublisherImprintName>
    <PublisherURL>http://www.springer.com</PublisherURL>
  </PublisherInfo>
  <Book Language="En" OutputMedium="All">
    <BookInfo BookProductType="Monograph" ContainsESM="No" Language="En" MediaType="eBook" NumberingDepth="1" NumberingStyle="ChapterOnly" OutputMedium="All" TocLevels="2">
      <BookID>978-3-319-09495-3</BookID>
      <BookTitle>Food Security Among Small-Scale Agricultural Producers in Southern Africa</BookTitle>
      <BookDOI>10.1007/978-3-319-09495-3</BookDOI>
      <BookTitleID>327825</BookTitleID>
      <BookPrintISBN>978-3-319-09494-6</BookPrintISBN>
      <BookElectronicISBN>978-3-319-09495-3</BookElectronicISBN>
      <BookEdition>2014</BookEdition>
      <BookChapterCount>7</BookChapterCount>
      <BookCopyright>
        <CopyrightHolderName>Springer International Publishing Switzerland</CopyrightHolderName>
        <CopyrightYear>2014</CopyrightYear>
      </BookCopyright>
      <BookSubjectGroup>
        <BookSubject Code="SCL" Type="Primary">Life Sciences</BookSubject>
        <BookSubject Code="SCL11006" Priority="1" Type="Secondary">Agriculture</BookSubject>
        <BookSubject Code="SC313000" Priority="2" Type="Secondary">Climate Change/Climate Change Impacts</BookSubject>
        <BookSubject Code="SCU34000" Priority="3" Type="Secondary">Sustainable Development</BookSubject>
        <BookSubject Code="SCJ12000" Priority="4" Type="Secondary">Economic Geography</BookSubject>
        <BookSubject Code="SC527010" Priority="5" Type="Secondary">Trade</BookSubject>
        <SubjectCollection Code="SUCO11642">Biomedical and Life Sciences</SubjectCollection>
      </BookSubjectGroup>
      <BookstoreLocation>Life Sciences</BookstoreLocation>
    </BookInfo>
    <BookHeader>
      <AuthorGroup>
        <Author AffiliationIDS="Aff1">
          <AuthorName DisplayOrder="Western">
            <GivenName>Josephine Phillip</GivenName>
            <FamilyName>Msangi</FamilyName>
          </AuthorName>
          <Contact>
            <Email>jpmsangi@iway.na</Email>
          </Contact>
        </Author>
        <Affiliation ID="Aff1">
          <OrgName>WELER Consulting Services</OrgName>
          <OrgAddress>
            <City>Windhoek Namibia</City>
            <Country>Namibia</Country>
          </OrgAddress>
        </Affiliation>
      </AuthorGroup>
    </BookHeader>
    <Chapter ID="b978-3-319-09495-3_7" Language="En" OutputMedium="All">
      <ChapterInfo ChapterType="OriginalPaper" ContainsESM="No" Language="En" NumberingDepth="1" NumberingStyle="ChapterOnly" OutputMedium="All" TocLevels="0">
        <ChapterID>7</ChapterID>
        <ChapterNumber>Chapter 7</ChapterNumber>
        <ChapterDOI>10.1007/978-3-319-09495-3_7</ChapterDOI>
        <ChapterSequenceNumber>7</ChapterSequenceNumber>
        <ChapterTitle Language="En">Climate-Smart Agriculture: Incorporating Weather Information into Small-Scale Agricultural Producers’ System: South Africa</ChapterTitle>
        <ChapterFirstPage>151</ChapterFirstPage>
        <ChapterLastPage>173</ChapterLastPage>
        <ChapterCopyright>
          <CopyrightHolderName>Springer International Publishing Switzerland</CopyrightHolderName>
          <CopyrightYear>2014</CopyrightYear>
        </ChapterCopyright>
        <ChapterHistory>
          <RegistrationDate>
            <Year>2014</Year>
            <Month>7</Month>
            <Day>16</Day>
          </RegistrationDate>
          <OnlineDate>
            <Year>2014</Year>
            <Month>8</Month>
            <Day>5</Day>
          </OnlineDate>
        </ChapterHistory>
        <ChapterContext>
          <BookID>978-3-319-09495-3</BookID>
          <BookTitle>Food Security Among Small-Scale Agricultural Producers in Southern Africa</BookTitle>
        </ChapterContext>
      </ChapterInfo>
      <ChapterHeader>
        <AuthorGroup>
          <Author AffiliationIDS="Aff2" CorrespondingAffiliationID="Aff2">
            <AuthorName DisplayOrder="Western">
              <GivenName>Josephine</GivenName>
              <GivenName>Phillip</GivenName>
              <FamilyName>Msangi</FamilyName>
            </AuthorName>
          </Author>
          <Affiliation ID="Aff2">
            <OrgName>WELER Consulting Services</OrgName>
            <OrgAddress>
              <City>Windhoek</City>
              <Country>Namibia</Country>
            </OrgAddress>
          </Affiliation>
        </AuthorGroup>
        <Abstract ID="Abs1" Language="En" OutputMedium="All">
          <Heading>Abstract</Heading>
          <Para TextBreak="No">Climate-smart agriculture is a site-specific and knowledge intensive concept that urges the world to pay attention to impacts of climate change on agriculture and food security by promoting sustainable practices that will increase agricultural productivity and build resilience to environmental pressures including adaptation to climate change. The need to meet food demands that support poor small-scale agricultural producers and enhance national food security and development goals is emphasized. Small-scale agricultural producers being the foundation of food security in many countries are able to respond innovatively to rapid changes and challenges provided they receive required policy and technological support. In Southern Africa it has been demonstrated that the small-scale agriculture as practiced in many parts is dynamic; the small-scale producers often come up with innovations that are the result of very complex long-term processes and networks without external interventions. However limited resources hamper meaningful advancement. Thus demand for appropriate policy and collaborative research to assist the small-scale agricultural producers attain success. Required is research that incorporates ideas and innovations evolving from the small-scale agricultural producers’ practices i.e. getting out of the traditional linear model where researchers provide the technologies that are supposed to be taken up by extension services that in turn wait for adoption by the producers. The Response Farming Project initiated to fortify the small-scale producers’ food security by helping them make optimal crop planning decisions through adapting their day-to-day management by responding to anticipated immediate on-hand crop-plant-weather situation and to the medium term forecasts for the coming weeks attest to the ability of small-scale producers to respond and adapt to weather and climate variability. Incorporating weather and climate forecasts as one of the factors to consider in the day to day management of the fields was largely embraced by most of the small-scale producers and extension officers. The participatory and collaborative project involving University researchers, the weather service, provincial departments of agriculture, extension officers, the producers and donor funding agency resulted in successful production of a maize crop under low and unpredictable rain conditions amidst high temperatures and resultant high evaporation rates.</Para>
        </Abstract>
        <KeywordGroup Language="En" OutputMedium="All">
          <Heading>Keywords</Heading>
          <Keyword>Climate-smart agriculture</Keyword>
          <Keyword>Participatory and collaborative research</Keyword>
          <Keyword>Response farming</Keyword>
          <Keyword>Weather forecasting</Keyword>
          <Keyword>Weather variability</Keyword>
          <Keyword>Sustainable agriculture</Keyword>
          <Keyword>Appropriate policy</Keyword>
          <Keyword>Dynamic agriculture, innovative response to weather and climate change</Keyword>
        </KeywordGroup>
      </ChapterHeader>
      <Body>
        <Section1 ID="Sec1">
          <Heading>Introduction</Heading>
          <Section2 ID="Sec2">
            <Heading>Climate-Smart Agriculture</Heading>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Climate-smart agriculture is a terminology coined by FAO in 2009 and refined during subsequent three global conferences first during the Global Conference on Agriculture, Food Security and Climate Change held in The Hague (October/November 2010); during a second conference held September 2012 in Viet Nam and a third conference held in Johannesburg, South Africa during December 2013. The first conference brought together the agendas of agriculture, food security and climate change while the second conference ministers of agriculture called for utilization of climate-smart agricultural practices to sustainably increase agricultural productivity and build resilience to environmental pressures while simultaneously assisting farmers to adapt to climate change while reducing greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">The purposes of the third conference were:
<OrderedList>
                <ListItem>
                  <ItemNumber>1.</ItemNumber>
                  <ItemContent>
                    <Para TextBreak="No">To promote a climate-smart agriculture alliance and share knowledge, information and good practices among public, private and civil society stakeholders as well as to promote the mainstreaming and up-scaling of climate-smart agriculture within the broader development goals.</Para>
                  </ItemContent>
                </ListItem>
                <ListItem>
                  <ItemNumber>2.</ItemNumber>
                  <ItemContent>
                    <Para TextBreak="No">To facilitate the implementation of concrete actions linking agriculture-related investments, policies, and measures with the transition to climate-smart agriculture.</Para>
                  </ItemContent>
                </ListItem>
                <ListItem>
                  <ItemNumber>3.</ItemNumber>
                  <ItemContent>
                    <Para TextBreak="No">To build global partnerships for resilience of agriculture, forestry and fisheries to climate change.</Para>
                  </ItemContent>
                </ListItem>
                <ListItem>
                  <ItemNumber>4.</ItemNumber>
                  <ItemContent>
                    <Para TextBreak="No">To promote the application of scientific solutions, information and policies conducive to increased and sustainable agricultural production yields, productivity and sustainable development.</Para>
                  </ItemContent>
                </ListItem>
                <ListItem>
                  <ItemNumber>5.</ItemNumber>
                  <ItemContent>
                    <Para TextBreak="No">To explore and share knowledge and responses of agriculture to climate change with emphasis on climate-smart agriculture, low carbon farming practices and conservation.</Para>
                  </ItemContent>
                </ListItem>
                <ListItem>
                  <ItemNumber>6.</ItemNumber>
                  <ItemContent>
                    <Para TextBreak="No">To search for new technological approaches conducive to productivity, adaptation and mitigation.</Para>
                  </ItemContent>
                </ListItem>
              </OrderedList>
            </Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">During the third conference, the World Resources Institute (WRI), United Nations Development program (UNDP), United Nations Environmental Program (UNEP) and the World Bank (WB) issued a report on achieving a sustainable food future. The report emphasizes the importance of reducing waste and demand for animal products, as well as following other climate-smart guidelines discussed during 2010 conference. The publication supports the call made earlier that “the world must meet food demands in a way that creates opportunities for the rural poor, limits clearing of forests, and reduces greenhouse gas emissions from agriculture”. The report reiterates that by reducing excessive demand for animal products, hundreds of millions of hectares of forests that would otherwise be cleared for grazing will be spared and land fertility levels restored. The report recommends that concerted efforts to improve soil and water management, improve pastureland productivity and restore degraded lands be formulated and where they exist, should be strengthened. The report further calls upon all actors to make extra efforts to raise awareness on better land management practices focusing on bringing the most inefficient farmers up to standard farming efficiency levels.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Climate-smart agriculture as coined by FAO in 2009 is defined as agriculture that sustainably increases productivity, resilience, reduces or removes Greenhouse Gases (GHGs), and enhances achievement of national food security and development goals. The approach is a further strengthening of ways to achieve the goals of sustainable development which focuses on economic, social and environmental dimensions. It is an approach geared towards developing technical, policy and investment conditions to achieve sustainable agricultural development for food security amidst climate change effects (FAO <CitationRef CitationID="CR4">2010</CitationRef>). It was recognized then that meeting the multiple objectives of climate-smart agriculture requires an integrated approach that is responsive to specific local conditions. As a new approach, climate-smart agriculture also targets strengthening livelihoods and food security, particularly those of small-scale producers by improving the management and use of natural resources and enabling them to adopt appropriate methods and technologies for the production, processing and marketing of agricultural goods. To maximize the benefits and minimize the tradeoffs, climate-smart agriculture takes into consideration the social, economic, and environmental context of the localities where it will be applied as well as repercussions on local resources.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Therefore, climate-smart agriculture is an approach that requires site-specific assessments to identify suitable agricultural production technologies and practices. The approach aims to prioritize and strengthen livelihoods of the small-scale producers through improving among others, access to services, knowledge, production resources, financial support and access to markets. Climate-smart agriculture interventions are highly location-specific and knowledge-intensive. Considerable efforts are required to develop the knowledge and capacities to make climate-smart agriculture a reality. In large part, these are the same efforts required for achieving sustainable agricultural development which have been pursued over several past decades. Climate-smart agriculture offers an opportunity to revitalize these efforts, overcome adoption barriers, while also adjusting them to the new realities of climate change.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">In 2010, FAO estimated that agricultural production will have to increase by 60 % by 2050 to meet expected global food demands. That is why it was deemed necessary that agricultural production be revolutionized in order to meet this demand and reduce poverty particularly in the developing countries including those in Africa. By 2010, Africa’s population had just passed one billion and was expected to double by 2050. Consequently, it was estimated that Africa will need to provide adequate food supplies to feed an additional over 20 million people each year and improve the nutritional status of more than 239 million people (Pye-Smith <CitationRef CitationID="CR8">2011</CitationRef>). At that time, it was recognized that developing countries as a whole and small-scale producers in particular were already grappling with the consequences of climate change and degraded natural resource base. Hence to ensure a food-secure future, farming must become climate resilient. Examples drawn from around the world and published in 2013 indicated that governments and communities have demonstrated willingness and ability to adopt innovations that would result in an improvement of lives of millions while reducing agriculture’s climate footprint. These incidences show the many ways climate-smart agriculture can take shape, and should serve as inspiration for future policies and investments (Neate <CitationRef CitationID="CR7">2013</CitationRef>).</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Although from the outset climate-smart agriculture appeared to be the answer to the predicament facing the global population particularly those in developing countries where most of the food is produced by resource poor small-scale agricultural producers, some reservations have been expressed by those who see difficulties in its implementation particularly the weight it gives to mitigation potentials. Serious doubts and concerns over the technical mitigation potentials revolve around whether funding will be forthcoming to enable the small-scale agricultural producers mitigate the challenges posed by climate change and rehabilitate their degraded fields so as to realize substantial increased land productivity. Another key reservation expressed entail challenges that must be tackled in order to register success in the long run including the fact that climate-smart agriculture practices require not only funding but also strong political leadership, supportive and coherent government policies and strategies, land tenure arrangements that make investments worthwhile, and, importantly, access to inputs and markets (FAC <CitationRef CitationID="CR2">2011a</CitationRef>).</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Those who expressed their reservations appreciates that these are not new challenges. On the contrary, they fully recognize that these challenges have been at the heart of debates on agricultural development for many decades but it has emerged very clearly that there are no quick fixes for any of them. Thus the main question is whether climate-smart agriculture will remain a distant dream, whether it will become another empty slogan, or whether it will lead to lasting improvements for the small-scale agricultural producers across Africa. While climate-smart agriculture presents an optimistic message of the future of agriculture in Africa, it however hinges on a belief that climate change can help facilitate changes that will lead not only to short term gains but also tackling the structural reasons for why small-scale agricultural producers in Africa have remained vulnerable over decades during when sustainable agriculture has been dominating the agenda of world organs (FAC <CitationRef CitationID="CR3">2011b</CitationRef>).</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Small-scale agricultural producers are the foundation of food security in many countries and an important part of the socio-economic and ecological landscape in many countries particularly in the developing world. Small-scale agricultural producers depend on family labour and mostly family resources to derive a large but variable share of their income and livelihoods. The land holdings are run by family members, a large proportion of which are headed by women and women play important roles in production, processing and marketing activities. Small-scale agricultural producers operate with scarce resources, especially land, which they use to generate a level of income that helps fulfil basic needs and achieve sustainable livelihoods (HLPE <CitationRef CitationID="CR5">2013</CitationRef>).</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Small-scale agricultural producers often resort to off-farm activities to augment their incomes and diversify risks, thus improving their resilience to the shocks that impact on agriculture; shocks such as droughts and pests invasion. During these times many small-scale agricultural producers rely on reciprocal family ties, kinship and social proximity. More often than not, small-scale agricultural producers produce for their subsistence and their food security is largely determined by their ability to meet food consumption needs and selling meager surpluses for cash generation. At the collective level, small-scale agricultural producers’ families are part of social networks within which mutual assistance and reciprocity translate into collective investments (mainly through work exchanges) and into solidarity systems. They also participate (when social factors and political freedom allows it) in rural producers’ organizations and local development associations in order to improve service provisions, including market access and market power, access to productive assets and to have a voice in public policy debates.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Small-scale agricultural producers contribute to food security and nutrition as well as to solving unemployment issues as they absorb family members who would otherwise be wondering the streets of urban centers looking for jobs which are hard to come by and in most cases non-existent. Small-scale agricultural producers effectively contribute towards a country’s food security by feeding the rural masses and in some cases where there is policy and public investments support can contribute effectively to food sovereignty and self sufficiency and significantly to economic growth. Small-scale agricultural producers also contribute towards poverty reduction, the emancipation of neglected and marginalized groups and the reduction of spatial and socio-economic inequalities. Where there is political and technological support, small-scale agricultural producers can contribute towards sustainable management of biodiversity and other natural resources while preserving their social and cultural heritage. Thus, small-scale agricultural producers directly and indirectly contribute towards world food security and nutrition as well as poverty reduction because they produce and sustain consumption of many rural households and in many instances serve as a source of food products for urban markets.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Meanwhile, it has been erroneously stated that small-scale agricultural producers often lack knowledge about potential options for adapting their production systems to climate change effects and have limited assets and risk-taking capacity to access and use appropriate technologies proposed by scientists and donors alike. It has also been hastily recommended that in order to enhance food security in the face of climate change, mitigation measures that would preserve the natural resource base and strengthen agricultural production systems should be considered so as to increase land productivity of small-scale agricultural producers. These statements need to be tested by examining specific locations and practices going on therein because in many instances these are blanket unsubstantiated conclusions. It is crucial that factors that affect the small-scale agricultural producers’ food security and their contribution towards a country’s food security be accorded the attention of researchers and technologists, policy planners and policy implementers who specialize in food production issues such as weather vagaries and risks including rainfall variability, unreliability and unpredictability.</Para>
          </Section2>
        </Section1>
        <Section1 ID="Sec3">
          <Heading>Climate-Smart Agriculture in Southern Africa</Heading>
          <Para TextBreak="No">It cannot be denied that agriculture in Southern Africa like in other developing countries ought to embrace predicted climate and weather changes and adopt new technologies in order to overcome food security impediments such as constant weather variability characterizing the region including predicted long term climate change. Responding to the predicted changes and adopting recommended interventions is what was referred to as “climate-smart agriculture” (FAO <CitationRef CitationID="CR4">2010</CitationRef>). Meanwhile it is safe to say that effective climate-smart practices are already being implemented in some parts of Southern Africa, what remains is injecting necessary changes that will strengthen these practices through scientific research and sourcing the required funding. These changes ought to be site specific addressing specific issues because of numerous micro variations that characterize the region. Changing small-scale agriculture is not only important for food security but also for reducing unemployment and mitigating poverty as well as for effective economic growth for the region.</Para>
          <Para TextBreak="No">Weather variability and subsequent climate change threatens the stability of food production and land productivity in large parts of Southern Africa. Long term changes in the patterns of temperature and precipitation, that are part of climate change, are expected to shift production seasons, pest and disease patterns, and modify the set of feasible crops affecting production, prices, incomes and ultimately, livelihoods and lives. In order to stabilize output and income, production systems must become more resilient, i.e. more capable of performing well in the face of disruptive events such as droughts and floods. More productive and resilient agriculture requires transformations in the management of natural resources (e.g. land, water, soil nutrients, and genetic resources) and higher efficiency in the use of these resources and inputs for production. In Southern Africa intensive research and scientific interventions are absolutely necessary.</Para>
          <Para TextBreak="No">The type of agricultural research required is research that incorporates ideas and innovations evolving from the small-scale agricultural producers’ practices i.e. getting out of the traditional linear model where researchers provide the technologies that are supposed to be taken up by extension services that in turn wait for adoption by the producers. Various attempts that are now emerging include those that seek to incorporate indigenous knowledge and recognize the small-scale agricultural producers’ capacity to identify and contribute to mitigations that would reduce rural poverty and improve food security. The small-scale agriculture as practiced in many parts of Southern Africa is said to be dynamic because the small-scale producers often come up with innovations that are the result of very complex long-term processes and networks. Many times these innovations occur without external interventions, they are often the outcome of the producers’ response to challenges such as the depletion of vital natural resources or when they seek to benefit from market opportunities. Researchers and policy makers and implementers should recognize this and put in place policies that encourage and support these innovations. Thus it is not only a question of involving small-scale agricultural producers in experiments; they must also be allowed to play their full part at every stage of agricultural research process from research priorities identification to interpretation and sharing the results and finally to implementation activities. The goal should be to encourage knowledge sharing and establish a strategy of dialogue between all interested parties, researchers, developers, donors and the small-scale producers themselves.</Para>
          <Para TextBreak="No">Generally, African small-scale agriculture has been described as dynamic because with little or no support from public research and development institutions, many small-scale agricultural producers are actively innovating individually and collectively to solve problems, improve their farming and income, and grasp opportunities. It is documented that small-scale agricultural producers respond in many innovative ways to the rapid changes and global challenges they face, including market competition, increasing and conflicting demands on use and management of land and water, and increasing unpredictability of weather. It is also documented that there are numerous ongoing innovative processes which show the capacity of small-scale agricultural producers to grasp opportunities, to create or access markets, to increase their resilience to risks and shocks, to manage natural resources in a responsible and sustainable way and to reshape urban–rural linkages. Yet many such initiatives take place “under the radar” or are ignored by state, non-state, private-sector and even organizations that unilaterally concentrate in developing and spreading agricultural technologies. Thus local innovations fitting the wide variety of contexts of African agriculture need to be recognized valued and encouraged (Letty et al. <CitationRef CitationID="CR6">2013</CitationRef>).</Para>
          <Para TextBreak="No">While formal research and development actors provide important elements, such as new knowledge and technologies, external inputs and other stimuli for innovation, the small-scale agricultural producers and other local stakeholders such as private business in the “real world” are better placed to identify key constraints and opportunities. They are also the ones who decide if and how to use and adapt the inputs from researchers and developers to their own context, so that innovation takes root and succeed. External interventions can play an important role in initiating and supporting innovation, but should avoid creating artificial enabling conditions and incentives (including market outlets) that are far removed from local realities and are short-lived and unsustainable. Such interventions may easily undermine the existing innovation dynamics and can seldom drive innovation over the longer term. Under such conditions, interventions should start with a thorough joint assessment with local actors of ongoing innovation processes in the area, looking for initiatives that should be supported, rather than ignoring or trying to bypass them.</Para>
          <Para TextBreak="No">In Southern Africa setting, research and innovation depends on social and organizational dimensions that are closely intertwined and therefore should be addressed jointly if innovation is to be successful. Taking a holistic view of innovation by supporting its multiple dimensions gives a better chance of achieving outcomes more relevant for small-scale agricultural producers and other local actors. Beside generating and transferring technology, support should hence go to enabling and accompanying organizational and institutional changes that make innovation possible in order that it may drive large-scale spread and adaptation of technology. For example, when market opportunities emerge or new value chains are possible, small-scale growers and processors respond eagerly if they have access to the resources and services to do so. Evolving consumer demand in terms of quantity and quality of products may also drive growers and other actors to develop new practices and relationships that promote access to food sources and income generation opportunities that stabilize their food security situation.</Para>
          <Para TextBreak="No">In Southern Africa several attempts have been made by development agencies including non-governmental agencies to come up with feasible interventions that address issues affecting productivity and food security of the small-scale agricultural producers. In certain circumstances where the suggested interventions (practices and techniques) were put forward without the input of the producers, ecological damage such as degradation of soils have resulted in lower and lower yields and have been a driver of small-scale agriculture encroachment into important natural ecological areas such as forests and land reserves. The small-scale agricultural producers’ quest to increase yields through expansion of land under cultivation without incorporating appropriate informed land management techniques often resulted in crop failures and increased vulnerability to climatic shocks such as droughts, floods and changing climate patterns. Research conducted in South Africa as part of French FIRCOP supported project involving small-scale food crop producers, participatory approaches demonstrated just how much success can be achieved if a holistic approach is employed. In this case, a participatory and collaborative project involving University researchers, the weather service provider, provincial departments of agriculture, extension officers, the small-scale agricultural producers and donor funding agency resulted in successful production of a maize crop under low and unpredictable rain conditions amidst high temperatures and resultant high evaporation rates (SADC <CitationRef CitationID="CR9">2009</CitationRef>).</Para>
        </Section1>
        <Section1 ID="Sec4">
          <Heading>Aim of the Project</Heading>
          <Para TextBreak="No">The aim of the Response Farming Project was to fortify the small-scale agricultural producers’ food security by helping them make optimal crop planning decisions through adapting their day-to-day management by responding to anticipated immediate on-hand crop-plant-weather situation and to the medium term forecasts for the coming weeks. The main purpose of the project was to enhance and sustain agricultural productivity and efficiency in the subsistence farming sector in South Africa. The main goals were to improve food security in poor rural communities; to help the small-scale producers to better manage agro-climatic risk and to alleviate poverty. It was envisaged that the project would contribute to achieving these goals by mitigating risks and improving efficiency of inputs which would result in cost savings in bad years (through applying less inputs), and achieving higher than normal production in good years (through applying greater inputs). This response made it possible to make important savings on inputs by applying inputs only when a good chance of success was envisaged. When drought risk was predicted, inputs such as fertilizer were reduced or their application postponed.</Para>
          <Para TextBreak="No">The Response Farming Project was based on responding to the immediate weather and climate conditions where the activities at farm level were altered or shifted in response to daily predicted weather conditions. Relevant farm management activities were recommended to the small-scale agricultural producers which gave them a chance to instantly change an activity (e.g. suspending weeding upon prediction of dry conditions or hurriedly harvesting a ripe crop upon prediction of excessive heavy rainfall). In this method, relevant input data like weather forecasts, amount of rainfall and physical status of the plants were deemed important in establishing the Response Farming System. In this project the weather forecasts were obtained from the South African Weather Service (SAWS) on a daily basis, whilst rainfall data and information on the physical condition of the fields were obtained directly from the small-scale agricultural producers. After data analysis and conversion of the weather forecast probabilities for different localities, recommendations were made and sent to the producers via SMS to their cell phones to advise them of the viable activities to be undertaken.</Para>
        </Section1>
        <Section1 ID="Sec5" Type="MaterialsAndMethods">
          <Heading>Project Methodology</Heading>
          <Section2 ID="Sec6">
            <Heading>Data Collection</Heading>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Selected sites for the project on response farming were located in the provinces of Mpumalanga and Limpopo, South Africa where dry land farming is threatened by various risks associated with particular weather conditions such as drought occurring in the middle of the growing period and thus affecting the output from the small-scale producers’ fields. The small-scale producers that were involved in the project were mostly women either working individually or together in community gardens. These producers had little capital and mainly manual tools. They worked on lands where potential for irrigation is limited or non-existent and their major preoccupation was to support their extended families. As such the project was designed to help resource-poor small-scale agricultural producers in coping with agro-climatological risks associated with dry land farming.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">In order to achieve the goal of this project, the necessary information (water balance of the individual producers’ fields, climate and weather forecasts and resulting recommendations) were given to the extension officers and the participating small-scale agricultural producers who were trained to understand and appreciate the recommendations and therefore were able to implement them. All the involved producers were able to understand the weather forecasts and how to interpret the recommendations. Both the small-scale agricultural producers and extension officers fully appreciated the environmental impacts of the agricultural activities as they had been trained on good practices to lessen natural resources’ degradation.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">The participatory approach afforded opportunities for resource poor small-scale agricultural producers to work together with crop specialists so that the producers learned by experience whilst the specialists became more aware of indigenous knowledge and other sociological aspects and beliefs which influence the producers decisions. Customarily, participatory research requires that all activities and recommendations are discussed between the producers and extension officers. As such during the planning of the research, the producers and the extension officers as well as the research scientists discussed relevant issues touching on crop varieties, planting density, planting conditions, and mixed cropping. The fieldwork was done by the producers while the research institutes covered the costs of inputs. Costs of additional labor were also covered by the research institutes depending on the individual situation. Two times a week, the producers received coded forecast by SMS, including recommendations (i.e. not orders).</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">The subproject supervisors made sure that they visited the small-scale agricultural producers at least twice a month at the start and during the growing season. These visits were used to discuss the given recommendations and to evaluate the actual crop status as well as to gauge the producer’s perceptions. The producers were visited by extension officers as frequently as possible in order to keep track of the developments and to collect appropriate data and information necessary for better project management. There were also interactive training sessions for the producers and the extension officers to enable better understanding of used methodologies. The producers’ concerns as well as challenges emanating from the project were discussed with the extension officers during these gatherings. Through a series of meetings with representatives from the departments of agriculture, a total of 12 sets of small-scale producers were selected from service centers which have different micro-climates, 4 in Limpopo and 8 in Mpumalanga. In total 108 producers were selected to participate in the project. A simple rain gauge (Fig. <InternalRef RefID="Fig1">7.1</InternalRef>) was installed in all selected sites.
<Figure Category="Standard" Float="Yes" ID="Fig1">
                <Caption Language="En">
                  <CaptionNumber>Fig. 7.1</CaptionNumber>
                  <CaptionContent>
                    <SimplePara>An extension officer beside a simple rain gauge at Mamvuka</SimplePara>
                  </CaptionContent>
                </Caption>
                <MediaObject ID="MO1">
                  <ImageObject Color="Color" FileRef="MediaObjects/327825_1_En_7_Fig1_HTML.jpg" Format="JPEG" Rendition="HTML" Type="Halftone"/>
                </MediaObject>
              </Figure>
            </Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Soil samples were taken at each and every field to determine the fertility and mineral deficiency in the soil. Samples were taken at more than five sites per field for the 0–15 cm upper soil depth and then mixed to find an average. The parameters measured were Phosphorus (P) content in mg/kg; Potassium (K) content in mg/kg and me/100 g; Calcium (Ca) content in mg/kg and me/100 g; Magnesium (Mg) content in mg/kg and me/100 g; Sodium (K) content in mg/kg and me/100 g; pH Resistance (ohms).</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">The main crop of interest to the project was maize as it was the staple food for most people in Limpopo and Mpumalanga. Cowpeas were added as a second crop to help the small-scale producers balance their diet and to introduce intercropping which was not commonly practiced in these rural areas. Yield from the cowpeas was not determined in the project because the producers constantly harvested the leaves which they used as a vegetable and thus undermined the ultimate grain yield (Fig. <InternalRef RefID="Fig2">7.2</InternalRef>).
<Figure Category="Standard" Float="Yes" ID="Fig2">
                <Caption Language="En">
                  <CaptionNumber>Fig. 7.2</CaptionNumber>
                  <CaptionContent>
                    <SimplePara>Planting maize at Phula, Mpumalanga</SimplePara>
                  </CaptionContent>
                </Caption>
                <MediaObject ID="MO2">
                  <ImageObject Color="Color" FileRef="MediaObjects/327825_1_En_7_Fig2_HTML.jpg" Format="JPEG" Rendition="HTML" Type="Halftone"/>
                </MediaObject>
              </Figure>
            </Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">The maize crop was planted first using a line spacing of 90 cm and row spacing of 40 cm and the second crop (cowpeas) was planted later. During the first year (2007/2008) the majority of the small-scale agricultural producers ended up only with maize crop because of the unavailability of cowpea seeds at the time of planting and subsequent dry spells during the season. During the second agricultural season (2008/2009), most of the small-scale agricultural producers from both provinces planted both maize and cowpeas. Planting of the fields started in mid-November 2007 and ended in mid-January 2008 for the Limpopo trials. In Mpumalanga, most producers planted during late November and December 2007. Due to germination problems some of the producers had to re-plant in January 2008.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Medium-term forecasts were obtained on a daily basis from the South Africa Weather Service (SAWS). The forecasts were presented in map format showing probability of light rainfall (&gt;1 mm), medium rainfall (&gt;5 mm) and heavy rainfall (over 20 mm). The images were then converted to percentage codes for each of the regions in order for the information to be shortened for SMS transmission. The coded SMSs contained four main parts, dates; weather types; rainfall probabilities and recommendations. Information was abbreviated so that the dates started with the abbreviation of the day of the week and the date of the first day of the weather forecast followed by the abbreviations of the day of the week until the end of the week according to Mellaart’s format. For example <Emphasis Type="Bold">W = 9 TFSSMT</Emphasis> indicates that the forecast is effective from Wednesday (W) the 9th followed by Thursday (T) up until the following Tuesday (T). Weather types were in the following code: f = fine, t = thunderstorm, r = rain, d = drizzle, p = partially cloudy, s = showers, c = cloudy and they appeared in the second row of the coded SMS, e.g. W <Emphasis Type="Bold">= 9 TFSSMT tcpffpt.</Emphasis> The first “t” and last “t” imply that there are thunderstorms expected on Wednesday the 9th and Tuesday the 15th.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">In the above example, rainfall probabilities were represented in deciles with 1 representing 10 % and 8 representing 80 % chance of rainfall. The probabilities were divided into three categories: the chances of rainfall exceeding 1 mm appeared in the second and third rows, the chances of rainfall exceeding 5 mm appeared in the fourth and fifth rows, and lastly, the chances of rainfall exceeding 20 mm in the sixth and seventh rows. The values in the second row showed probability of rain for 7 days starting on Wednesday, while the third row showed the chances of rainfall in the second week preceded by “2w” which is a symbol for second week. The seasonal forecast was obtained during the beginning of the season from the SAWS as well as the monthly updates. This information was helpful in providing the expected cumulative 3-monthly rainfall for the season. The small-scale agricultural producers and extension officers were advised in advance of the expected rainfall in the next 3–6 months of the agricultural season.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">To make recommendations on the farming actions, the data considered included the plant development stage because the stage of the plant growth was key in determining the recommendations to be made as normally the plant responds differently to a weather phenomenon depending on its growth stage as well as the pertaining state of the field due to the fact that usually the state of the field is also crucial in tailored recommendations. The extent of the weeds coverage, level of pest infestation and moisture content are some of the physical environmental properties of the field which had to be considered before making any recommendations. During the pre-season, seasonal forecasts were viewed which gave an indication of how the season might be for the entire region. These earlier forecasts also helped to determine the seed varieties to be used. During the season, the 2-week forecasts formed the integral part of the Response Farming decision-making system.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Harvesting for each plot, yield data was obtained from a random sample of size 10 m × 10 m but in some places the whole field was harvested. Figure <InternalRef RefID="Fig3">7.3</InternalRef> shows accumulated harvest data from one of the fields during the 2007/2008 agricultural season. All the cobs were harvested and counted. Three to six samples of 20 cobs were then weighed to obtain the average weight of one cob (Fig. <InternalRef RefID="Fig4">7.4</InternalRef>). Three to six cobs were also selected randomly; the grains were then removed and counted to obtain the average number of grains per cob (Fig. <InternalRef RefID="Fig5">7.5</InternalRef>). A further 3–6 samples of 200 grains were weighed to obtain the average weight of one grain (Fig. <InternalRef RefID="Fig6">7.6</InternalRef>). Moisture content of the three samples was determined using a grain moisture meter (Figs. <InternalRef RefID="Fig7">7.7</InternalRef> and <InternalRef RefID="Fig8">7.8</InternalRef>).
<Figure Category="Standard" Float="Yes" ID="Fig3">
                <Caption Language="En">
                  <CaptionNumber>Fig. 7.3</CaptionNumber>
                  <CaptionContent>
                    <SimplePara>Maize cobs harvested at one of the fields in Limpopo</SimplePara>
                  </CaptionContent>
                </Caption>
                <MediaObject ID="MO3">
                  <ImageObject Color="Color" FileRef="MediaObjects/327825_1_En_7_Fig3_HTML.jpg" Format="JPEG" Rendition="HTML" Type="Halftone"/>
                </MediaObject>
              </Figure>
              <Figure Category="Standard" Float="Yes" ID="Fig4">
                <Caption Language="En">
                  <CaptionNumber>Fig. 7.4</CaptionNumber>
                  <CaptionContent>
                    <SimplePara>Weighing of cobs, Limpopo</SimplePara>
                  </CaptionContent>
                </Caption>
                <MediaObject ID="MO4">
                  <ImageObject Color="Color" FileRef="MediaObjects/327825_1_En_7_Fig4_HTML.jpg" Format="JPEG" Rendition="HTML" Type="Halftone"/>
                </MediaObject>
              </Figure>
              <Figure Category="Standard" Float="Yes" ID="Fig5">
                <Caption Language="En">
                  <CaptionNumber>Fig. 7.5</CaptionNumber>
                  <CaptionContent>
                    <SimplePara>Counting of grains</SimplePara>
                  </CaptionContent>
                </Caption>
                <MediaObject ID="MO5">
                  <ImageObject Color="Color" FileRef="MediaObjects/327825_1_En_7_Fig5_HTML.jpg" Format="JPEG" Rendition="HTML" Type="Halftone"/>
                </MediaObject>
              </Figure>
              <Figure Category="Standard" Float="Yes" ID="Fig6">
                <Caption Language="En">
                  <CaptionNumber>Fig. 7.6</CaptionNumber>
                  <CaptionContent>
                    <SimplePara>Weighing of grains</SimplePara>
                  </CaptionContent>
                </Caption>
                <MediaObject ID="MO6">
                  <ImageObject Color="Color" FileRef="MediaObjects/327825_1_En_7_Fig6_HTML.jpg" Format="JPEG" Rendition="HTML" Type="Halftone"/>
                </MediaObject>
              </Figure>
              <Figure Category="Standard" Float="Yes" ID="Fig7">
                <Caption Language="En">
                  <CaptionNumber>Fig. 7.7</CaptionNumber>
                  <CaptionContent>
                    <SimplePara>Measuring grain moisture content</SimplePara>
                  </CaptionContent>
                </Caption>
                <MediaObject ID="MO7">
                  <ImageObject Color="Color" FileRef="MediaObjects/327825_1_En_7_Fig7_HTML.jpg" Format="JPEG" Rendition="HTML" Type="Halftone"/>
                </MediaObject>
              </Figure>
              <Figure Category="Standard" Float="Yes" ID="Fig8">
                <Caption Language="En">
                  <CaptionNumber>Fig. 7.8</CaptionNumber>
                  <CaptionContent>
                    <SimplePara>Grain moisture meter reading</SimplePara>
                  </CaptionContent>
                </Caption>
                <MediaObject ID="MO8">
                  <ImageObject Color="Color" FileRef="MediaObjects/327825_1_En_7_Fig8_HTML.jpg" Format="JPEG" Rendition="HTML" Type="Halftone"/>
                </MediaObject>
              </Figure>
            </Para>
          </Section2>
        </Section1>
        <Section1 ID="Sec7" Type="Results">
          <Heading>Data Analysis Results and Discussion</Heading>
          <Section2 ID="Sec8">
            <Heading>Rainfall Data Analysis</Heading>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Long-term cumulative seasonal rainfall records show that the western parts had low cumulative rainfall of less than 400 mm (October to April). These sites in the western parts were more prone to extended dry spells while the other trial sites situated in the eastern and central parts recorded long-term mean seasonal rainfall between 500 mm and 600 mm. There were few sites which fell on a higher rainfall zone of 600–700 mm. Cumulative rainfall for Mpumalanga trial sites showed the majority of the sites as being in the 600–700 mm rainfall zone while a few others had seasonal rainfall normally above 700 mm. The interpolated mean surfaces shown in Figs. <InternalRef RefID="Fig9">7.9</InternalRef> and <InternalRef RefID="Fig10">7.10</InternalRef> show the average seasonal rainfall for the sites and thus in other years (El Nino years) the seasonal rainfall would be lower than normal while in favorable years (neutral &amp; La Nina years) the seasonal rainfall would be normal to above-normal.
<Figure Category="Standard" Float="Yes" ID="Fig9">
                <Caption Language="En">
                  <CaptionNumber>Fig. 7.9</CaptionNumber>
                  <CaptionContent>
                    <SimplePara>Long-term seasonal rainfall for Limpopo sites</SimplePara>
                  </CaptionContent>
                </Caption>
                <MediaObject ID="MO9">
                  <ImageObject Color="Color" FileRef="MediaObjects/327825_1_En_7_Fig9_HTML.gif" Format="GIF" Rendition="HTML" Type="Linedraw"/>
                </MediaObject>
              </Figure>
              <Figure Category="Standard" Float="Yes" ID="Fig10">
                <Caption Language="En">
                  <CaptionNumber>Fig. 7.10</CaptionNumber>
                  <CaptionContent>
                    <SimplePara>Long-term seasonal rainfall for Mpumalanga sites</SimplePara>
                  </CaptionContent>
                </Caption>
                <MediaObject ID="MO10">
                  <ImageObject Color="Color" FileRef="MediaObjects/327825_1_En_7_Fig10_HTML.gif" Format="GIF" Rendition="HTML" Type="Linedraw"/>
                </MediaObject>
              </Figure>
            </Para>
          </Section2>
          <Section2 ID="Sec9">
            <Heading>Soil Sample Results</Heading>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Soil fertility results for the Limpopo trial sites showed that most of the fields had deficiency of phosphorus (P). The potassium (K) content in most of the fields was moderate to high. A few exceptions were noted where P and K deviated slightly from those recorded in most of the fields. The content of micro-elements like calcium (Ca), magnesium (Mg) and sodium (Na) were moderate to high in all the fields. The pH of the soil was neutral with a slight bias to acidic. Fertilizer recommendations were made taking these findings into consideration. The soil mineral content in Mpumalanga trial sites also showed deficiency in P in most fields with the exception of one field which had moderate P content. Potassium content was mostly moderate with values below 60 mg/kg. The levels of micro-elements were low to moderate at all the Mpumalanga sites with neutral pH.</Para>
          </Section2>
          <Section2 ID="Sec10">
            <Heading>Crop Water Requirement</Heading>
            <Para TextBreak="No">During the first agricultural season most planting was done late with the earliest planting in the second dekad of November (21–30 Nov). The latest planting dates were between 1 January and 10 January. The water requirement satisfaction index (WRSI), which is a measure of how the water requirement of maize were met, show unsatisfactory results for all the trial sites in Limpopo with the exceptions of two sites where the water requirement was marginally met (70–80 %). At the few sites where cumulative seasonal rainfall exceeded the cumulative crop water requirement, the index value was not at maximum value (100 %) because the rainfall was not distributed according to crop water requirement. However in the second agricultural season the crop water requirement was achieved as in all the fields the seasonal rainfall exceeded the seasonal crop water requirement. The number of dekads with water deficit was comparatively lower than that experienced in the first (2007–2008) agricultural season.</Para>
          </Section2>
          <Section2 ID="Sec11">
            <Heading>Grain Yield</Heading>
            <Para TextBreak="No">All the grain yield values were calculated at a moisture content of 12.5 %. During the 2007/2008 season, at some places the yield was very low, around 0.3 t/ha. This low yield was mainly attributed to the very late weeding at the critical phenological stage i.e. vegetative stage (Fig. <InternalRef RefID="Fig11">7.11</InternalRef>). Where better field management was practiced and the recommendations were followed closely, much higher yields (&gt;3 t/ha) were recorded (Fig. <InternalRef RefID="Fig12">7.12</InternalRef>).
<Figure Category="Standard" Float="Yes" ID="Fig11">
                <Caption Language="En">
                  <CaptionNumber>Fig. 7.11</CaptionNumber>
                  <CaptionContent>
                    <SimplePara>Poor crop due to late weeding at Malonga, Limpopo, in 2007</SimplePara>
                  </CaptionContent>
                </Caption>
                <MediaObject ID="MO11">
                  <ImageObject Color="Color" FileRef="MediaObjects/327825_1_En_7_Fig11_HTML.jpg" Format="JPEG" Rendition="HTML" Type="Halftone"/>
                </MediaObject>
              </Figure>
              <Figure Category="Standard" Float="Yes" ID="Fig12">
                <Caption Language="En">
                  <CaptionNumber>Fig. 7.12</CaptionNumber>
                  <CaptionContent>
                    <SimplePara>Health crop due to early weeding at Mashamba, Limpopo, in 2007</SimplePara>
                  </CaptionContent>
                </Caption>
                <MediaObject ID="MO12">
                  <ImageObject Color="Color" FileRef="MediaObjects/327825_1_En_7_Fig12_HTML.jpg" Format="JPEG" Rendition="HTML" Type="Halftone"/>
                </MediaObject>
              </Figure>
            </Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">The 2008/2009 agricultural season resulted in an overall increase in maize yield in most places due to better understanding of methodologies even though the seasonal rainfall was low and its distribution was also uneven. During this season, some of the fields recorded less maize yields than the yields obtained in the previous season mainly due to the infestation of birds at emergence and monkeys at silking stage. At this site planting occurred way before the surrounding producers not participating in the project and thus all the birds and monkeys seriously affected the resulting harvest. Some of the affected fields had to be re-planted as a result of birds eating emerging plants/seeds. However, on the whole there was a great deal of improvement in maize yield (1.1–2.3 t/ha). In a few cases, the producers harvested the fields without informing the project leader and in others animals destroyed all the harvest because of inadequate fencing; so that no yields were recorded. The yield of cowpeas was not calculated because the producers progressively harvested the leaves as well as the green peas for their home consumption.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">The final harvests indicated the extent to which the recommendations resulted in reducing risk and minimizing unnecessary inputs. Measurements of production made to ascertain food security showed that in most fields the harvest exceeded the normal harvest obtained during previous years during when only traditional knowledge and traditional methods were used to manage crop growing.</Para>
          </Section2>
        </Section1>
        <Section1 ID="Sec12" Type="Conclusion">
          <Heading>Challenges, Conclusions and Recommendations</Heading>
          <Section2 ID="Sec13">
            <Heading>Project Challenges</Heading>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Several challenges were faced in this project. Some of the participating small-scale agricultural producers found it difficult to treat response farming plots differently from the rest of their fields and lacked consistence, hence making it difficult to distinctly differentiate between the producer-managed plots and the response farming plots. In some cases crop losses were experienced due to invasions by both wild and domestic animals; in a few cases the producers lost all their produce. Furthermore at a few of the producers’ fields, rainfall recording was not properly done making it difficult to analyze rainfall data. Similarly, measurements of the growth rate and weed infestation were inconsistent in a few fields.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">More challenges arose where communication problems arose in some of the fields and the producers unilaterally took major decisions like harvesting without informing project managers. It would have been ideal for all the fields to have planted the two crops recommended for the project i.e. maize and cowpeas, but unavailability of seeds and persistent dry spells delayed and even prevented the planting of the second crop at some places. Tractor availability was a common constraint in most places as there were few tractors in the project areas where demand was high especially during the early parts of the rainfall season. In addition, excessive rainfall made it difficult for tractors to work in some areas. Disagreements within some of the community gardens restricted full participation by all members; as a result some of the important tasks like weeding were not done satisfactorily.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Further challenges arose from the fact that some of the recommendations included in the messages that were sent to the producers were not adhered to without any valid reasons. Varying literacy levels as well as understanding of simple scientific approaches among the small-scale agricultural producers was a challenge to the project administrators as the producers had to be reminded regularly on the objectives of the project. The Limpopo trial sites were over 400 km away from the agriculture research offices and this resulted to a lag on the response to problems and delivery of inputs. Another constraint was the inability by the scientists to speak local languages in both Limpopo and Mpumalanga.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">The project thus recommended that the assistance of NGOs like EcoLink which focus on small-scale agricultural producers should be exploited fully to help the producers have access to recommended crop varieties. Further, it was recommended that the legislation governing farming activities take cognizance of the interaction between socio-economic factors and climatic variations when implementing the response farming methodology in different regions and countries to establish the potential and advantages of the method. Research on reducing risk is important in order to combat the inherent problems linked with then persistent increase in HIV/AIDS and decline in farming labor force as well as meeting the requirement to have improved diet. Additionally, the then large reductions in government drought relief in South Africa placed the responsibility of producing enough food to meet diet requirements of the resource poor population squarely on the shoulders of the small-scale agricultural producers; hence the need that they learn how to handle the climatic risks facing them. Furthermore, it was recommended that mixed cropping using leguminous crops such as groundnuts or cowpeas which fortify food supply and improve soil fertility whilst reducing production risks be incorporated into extension services packages.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">At the time of the research, unemployment was rife in the selected areas where most small-scale producers were women who had slim prospects of securing formal employment. Hence the project could improve conditions for these vulnerable members of the population by potentially enabling them to produce more of their own food and eventually generate an income from selling any accruing surplus.</Para>
          </Section2>
          <Section2 ID="Sec14">
            <Heading>Project Conclusions</Heading>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Generally, small-scale agricultural producers have restricted resources and they therefore tend to lower inputs to avoid cost increase but end up lowering yields from their pieces of land. The yield is also affected by variable weather conditions inherent in the area. Therefore to lower the risks and ensure better yields it was made sure that the producers received appropriate information and had access to those crop varieties which are most suited to that area. Response Farming research carried out during 2000–2006 by Mellaart had shown that small-scale producers are usually willing to use improved new crop varieties. Non-use is attributed to lack of access to improved seed varieties which forces them to grow crop varieties which are available locally (SADC <CitationRef CitationID="CR9">2009</CitationRef>).</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Although it was highly challenging to work with this sector of the farming community in South Africa, it emerged that the method helped a large group of resource-poor agricultural producers and improved output from their small plots of land. The incorporation of weather and climate forecasts as one of the factors to consider in the day to day management of the fields was largely embraced by most of the small-scale agricultural producers and extension officers. The producers and extension officers showed great interest and ability in grasping the principles of response farming after the training workshops that took place during mid-season.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Use of indigenous languages made it easy for the small-scale agricultural producers and the extension officers to understand the methodology. Those producers who were more dedicated in implementing the response farming methodology received better yields than those who were not so committed. However most of the producers displayed great interest in knowing the soil fertility of their fields as well as how they could improve their soils following the information sessions. Frequently the producers including large-scale agricultural producers not involved in the project requested for the information provided to those in the project which was a good indication that the response farming approach had yielded visible benefits to the participating small-scale agricultural producers. Meanwhile the scientists grasped the benefits of indigenous knowledge and beliefs which still play an important role in agricultural production in the rural areas. Better understanding of these aspects by the scientist definitely closed the gap between indigenous knowledge and science.</Para>
          </Section2>
          <Section2 ID="Sec15">
            <Heading>Project Recommendations</Heading>
            <Para TextBreak="No">It was recommended that in future communications between the researchers and the small-scale agricultural producers should be conducted in local languages to enhance interpretation of the forecast recommendations. The participation of the small-scale agricultural producers is essential in improving the Response Farming system. It was further recommended that the growers be assisted with basic funding to meet basic needs such as mending gates and fences to their field to minimize losses from animal invasion and thefts which were rampant at some of the fields. Furthermore, it was recommended that in the future, socio-economic analysis should be included in the evaluation of the project to assess the real benefits of the project. The amount of money spent on manpower hours, in the purchase of fertilizer and other inputs, payment of casual labor for weeding and harvesting should be compared to the monetary value of the harvest to determine the actual benefit of using the methodology in managing crop production. It would be more profitable to include dissemination of weather and climate forecasts to cooperatives and unions in order to feed more producers with climate information to help them improve their productivity. All members of the cooperative or union should be given tailored information with a low level of complexity.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">It was further recommended to urgently upgrade and finance national research and extension systems targeted specifically to the needs of small-scale producers, with supporting financial mechanisms. The main objective would be to increase productivity and resilience through diversification of the production system with a high concern for the self-provision of diverse foods with a high nutritional value. Combining increased productivity and resilience will require a high level of investment in research to develop productive land-use systems with minimal ecological risk such that biodiversity may be used productively. Agricultural research and extension should support the in-situ and ex-situ conservation of agricultural biodiversity in the context of climate change. Small-scale producers need appropriate seeds as well as machinery for field operation, food processing and other value-adding transformations. International collaboration and the sharing of experiences in technology development for small-scale producers in different regions of the world should be promoted with a strong engagement, if not leadership, of small-scale producers’ organizations.</Para>
          </Section2>
          <Section2 ID="Sec16">
            <Heading>General Conclusions and Recommendations</Heading>
            <Para TextBreak="No">While small-scale agricultural producers are the main investors in their own agriculture system, they face many investment constraints that are specific to their situation. First, self-provision of food remains a key component of the food security strategies of their production system; it is both an asset and a constraint to generation of income and capacity to invest. Second, their risk-prone environment is a double threat to investments, first by reducing the expected output generated from agriculture, and thus limiting their own capacity to invest, and second by the need to sell some of their existing assets to cover urgent needs when there is a shock. On the productive side, technical risks owing to plant pests, animal diseases, climate variability, rainfall irregularity and floods combine with market price volatility to reduce the expected output from their land holdings.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Meanwhile, all small-scale agricultural producers have to make investments in seeds, fertilizers and labor for current production yet limited income and assets constrain both direct investments and access to credit. Natural and production hazards may lead to increased indebtedness. Family labor is often diverted towards more remunerative off-farm activities such as paid employment. In the small-scale agricultural producers’ holdings the family side and the productive and economic sides are closely intertwined: domestic or family risks such as illness, or life-related events such as marriage, may lead to a reduction in productive assets in order to cope with such needs.</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">In most cases small-scale producers are keen to invest in agriculture to improve their performance if minimum conditions are met. First of these conditions is the capacity to access diversified assets without reducing family consumption below a critical level. Second is a secure environment that provides expectations of improvement in the technical and economic performances of the land holding at their disposal. Third is to enjoy improved standard of living conditions regarding access to public or private services and to consider that living in the rural areas depending on agriculture is a viable option. This minimum set of conditions implies that continues investments by small-scale agricultural producers require injected investments by both private and public institutions. Private institutions should have an interest in investing in rural areas, while public investment is needed to guarantee access to basic services and convince the small-scale agricultural producers to remain in the rural areas when they see prospects of more decent living in rural areas. Migration to towns will cease if the third condition is fulfilled (Chamberlin and Jayne <CitationRef CitationID="CR1">2012</CitationRef>).</Para>
            <Para TextBreak="No">Agricultural advisors and research scientists are in a key position to be brokers of innovation processes and to provide a host of other support services to innovation initiatives of small-scale agricultural producers and local enterprises. However, they need to have an explicit mandate for playing such roles, while their capacities to do so need to be strengthened by adequate funding, relevant policies and regulations governing the small-scale agriculture sector (Waters-Bayer <CitationRef CitationID="CR10">2011</CitationRef>). Renewed investment in rural advisory services is needed, and institutional support for advisors to be able to play a brokerage role in innovation processes has to be firmly integrated at all levels in the advisory services. Universities, colleges and vocational schools play a major role in preparing future and current researchers, rural advisors, small-scale agricultural producers’ leaders and local government staff through initial and continuing education. To build capacities, educational and training institutions need to interact closely on the ground with small-scale agricultural producers, rural communities, entrepreneurs, advisors, researchers and government staff. Students, teachers and all stakeholders should be exposed to innovation dynamics in small-scale agriculture and should learn how to see and analyze the processes, contribute to documenting and understanding how agricultural innovation happens, and acquire the skills needed to support it.</Para>
          </Section2>
        </Section1>
      </Body>
      <BodyRef FileRef="978-3-319-09495-3_Chapter_7.pdf" OutputMedium="Online" PDFType="Typeset" TargetType="OnlinePDF"/>
      <ChapterBackmatter>
        <Bibliography ID="Bib1">
          <Heading>References</Heading>
          <Citation ID="CR1">
            <BibUnstructured>Chamberlin J, Jayne TS (2012) Unpacking the, meaning of “Market Access”. World development, vol 41, Jan 2013. <ExternalRef>
                <RefSource>www.afre.msu.edu/people/chamberlin_jordan</RefSource>
                <RefTarget Address="http://www.afre.msu.edu/people/chamberlin_jordan" TargetType="URL"/>
              </ExternalRef>. Accessed 19 Sep 2013</BibUnstructured>
          </Citation>
          <Citation ID="CR2">
            <BibUnstructured>FAC (2011a) Agriculture and climate change in the UN climate negotiations. FAC policy brief. <ExternalRef>
                <RefSource>www.future-agricultures.org/component/content/article/38-blog/</RefSource>
                <RefTarget Address="http://www.future-agricultures.org/component/content/article/38-blog/" TargetType="URL"/>
              </ExternalRef>. Accessed 2 Dec 2013</BibUnstructured>
          </Citation>
          <Citation ID="CR3">
            <BibUnstructured>FAC (2011b) Climate smart agriculture: The new holy grail of agricultural development. Future agriculture consortium. <ExternalRef>
                <RefSource>http://www.future-agricultures.org/component/content/article/38-blog/7643-climate-smart-agriculture-the-new-holy-grail-of-agricultural-development#.Up3vcMLxs5s</RefSource>
                <RefTarget Address="http://www.future-agricultures.org/component/content/article/38-blog/7643-climate-smart-agriculture-the-new-holy-grail-of-agricultural-development#.Up3vcMLxs5s" TargetType="URL"/>
              </ExternalRef>. Accessed 5 Dec 2013</BibUnstructured>
          </Citation>
          <Citation ID="CR4">
            <BibUnstructured>FAO (2010) Climate-smart agriculture: policies practices and financing for food security, adaptation and mitigation. The Hague conference on agriculture, food security and climate change. <ExternalRef>
                <RefSource>www.fao.org/fileadmin/user_upload/newsroom/docs/the-hague</RefSource>
                <RefTarget Address="http://www.fao.org/fileadmin/user_upload/newsroom/docs/the-hague" TargetType="URL"/>
              </ExternalRef>. Accessed 30 Nov 2013</BibUnstructured>
          </Citation>
          <Citation ID="CR5">
            <BibUnstructured>HLPE (2013) Investing in smallholder agriculture for food security: a report by the high level panel of experts on food security and nutrition. <ExternalRef>
                <RefSource>http://paepard.blogspot.fr/2013/12/investing-in-smallholder-agriculture.html</RefSource>
                <RefTarget Address="http://paepard.blogspot.fr/2013/12/investing-in-smallholder-agriculture.html" TargetType="URL"/>
              </ExternalRef>. Accessed 12 June 2013</BibUnstructured>
          </Citation>
          <Citation ID="CR6">
            <BibUnstructured>Letty B, Stevens J, Rootman G, Buthelezi N, Jagiello W, Triomphe B (2013) Experiences from JOLISAA: three cases of multi-stakeholder innovation processes in South Africa. <ExternalRef>
                <RefSource>http://www.sasae.co.za/pdf/JOLISAA%20policy%20brief%20DINA4%20low%20density.pdf</RefSource>
                <RefTarget Address="http://www.sasae.co.za/pdf/JOLISAA%2520policy%2520brief%2520DINA4%2520low%2520density.pdf" TargetType="URL"/>
              </ExternalRef>. Accessed 22 Jan 2014</BibUnstructured>
          </Citation>
          <Citation ID="CR7">
            <BibUnstructured>Neate P (2013) Climate-smart agriculture success stories from farming communities Around the world. CGIAR and CTA, Wageningen. <ExternalRef>
                <RefSource>http://www.farmingfirst.org/tag/climate-smart-agriculture/</RefSource>
                <RefTarget Address="http://www.farmingfirst.org/tag/climate-smart-agriculture/" TargetType="URL"/>
              </ExternalRef>. Accessed 4 Dec 2013</BibUnstructured>
          </Citation>
          <Citation ID="CR8">
            <BibUnstructured>Pye-Smith C (2011) Farming’s climate-smart future: placing agriculture at the heart of climate-change policy. CGIAR and CTA. Wageningen. <ExternalRef>
                <RefSource>http://ccafs.cgiar.org/publications/farmings-climate-smart-future-placing-agriculture-heart-climate-change-policy#.Uybor2KKAfQ</RefSource>
                <RefTarget Address="http://ccafs.cgiar.org/publications/farmings-climate-smart-future-placing-agriculture-heart-climate-change-policy#.Uybor2KKAfQ" TargetType="URL"/>
              </ExternalRef>. Accessed 4 Dec 2013</BibUnstructured>
          </Citation>
          <Citation ID="CR9">
            <BibUnstructured>SADC (2009) Adapting day to day management of subsistence and small-scale farming to weather and climate forecast to optimize inputs and reduce drought risks. Final FIRCOP project report, Project 8</BibUnstructured>
          </Citation>
          <Citation ID="CR10">
            <BibUnstructured>Waters-Bayer A (2011) Farmer-managed innovation funds drive multi-stakeholder learning processes. In: CTA/GFRAS international conference “Innovations in Extension and Advisory Services”, Nairobi. <ExternalRef>
                <RefSource>extensionconference2011.cta.int/programme/session3/networks/1</RefSource>
                <RefTarget Address="http://extensionconference2011.cta.int/programme/session3/networks/1" TargetType="URL"/>
              </ExternalRef>
            </BibUnstructured>
          </Citation>
        </Bibliography>
      </ChapterBackmatter>
    </Chapter>
  </Book>
</Publisher>
